A Guide to the Phoebus A.T. Levene papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA174
Rockefeller Archive Center
Phoebus A.T. Levene papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1905-1940
Rockefeller Archive Center
Levene, P. A. T. (Phoebus Aaron)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA174
8.36 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Phoebus Aaron Theodor Levene, 1869-1940, physician and chemist in proteins and nucleic acids, carbohydrates and lipoids at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research until his death in 1940.
Biographical note
1869 Born February 25, Sagor, Russia
1891 M.D. Imperial Military Medical Academy, St. Petersburg
1892 Arrived in the United States Practiced medicine
1896-1905 Associate in chemistry, State Pathological Institute, New York
1900-1902 Chemist, Saranac Laboratory for Study of Tuberculosis, Saranac, New York
1905-1906 Herter Lecturer in pathological chemistry, New York University, New York
1905 Assistant in Chemistry, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York, New York
1907 Member, RIMR
1931 Willard Gibbs Medal, American Chemical Society, Chicago section
1938 William H. Nichols Medal, American Chemical Society, New York sect.
1939 Member Emeritus, RIMR
1940 Died September 6, New York, N.Y.
General note
Van der Scheer-Landsteiner Peptides - Bergmann Carbobenzoxy Method (Note: Given to R. Bruce Merrifield 8/13/84 as historical materials by H.W. Chase).
d,1 Leucine Kahlbaum recrystallized
Leucine methyl ester. HC1 M.P. 143° 12/27/38
p-Nitrobenzoyl glycyl-glycine M.P. 223-224° 17 gm 11/7/37
-Aminobenzoyl glycyl-glycine M.P. 307 (inactive)
Glycyl-d, l-leucine pure 5gm
Leucyl-leucine Marker 5.5gm
d, l, Alanylglycine (Abderhalden)
Diglycyl-glycine pure 5 gm.
Diglycyl-d, l,-leucine pure 8 gm.
Diglycyl-leucyl amine 1.9 gm acetone recrystallized 11/10/39
d, l-Leucyl-glycyl-glycine pure 5gm
Leucyl-diglycine ethyl ester
d, l- Leucyl-glycyl-glycine methyl ester. HC1 M.P. 208-209
Triglycyl-glycine pure 3.6 gm
Triglycyl-d, 1-leucine pure 4 gm
Glycyl-d, l-leucyl-glycyl-glycine 4/18/33 N=18.02%
Glycyl-glycyl-l-glutamyl glycine
Tetraglycyl-glycine pure (analyzed)
d, 1-Leucyl-triglycyl-glycine pure 36 gm.
Diglycyl-leucyl-glycyl-glycine (inact) Made with Cbzo glycyl-glycine azide and leucyl-glycyl-glycine
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 L657
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Biochemistry; Life sciences; Nucleic acids; Chemistry; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Lipids; Biology -- Research; Carbohydrates; Medicine, Preventive; Medical education; Medical research; Medical sciences; Levene, P. A. T. (Phoebus Aaron); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Biographical items; photographs, bibliography, administrative correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  One box of material consists primarily of administrative correspondence between P.A.T. Levene and Simon Flexner and the Business Manager during 35 years at The Rockefeller Institute. One folder is devoted to biographical items including photographs of Levene, of his laboratory, some of the workers in his laboratory and a photograph of Dr. Levene with Pavlov and Pavlov's son and Simon Flexner. Also included is a photographic copy of a signed book prepared by his associates and presented on his 70th birthday; obituary items; funeral arrangements and list of books presented to the Institute by Mrs. Levene at the time of Dr. Levene's death.
  Includes NAS BIOGRAPHICAL MEMOIR by D.D. Van Slyke and Walter Jacobs V. 23 (1944).
  Related Materials
  Related items can be found in the following Record Groups: 210. 3 (1); Acetone (listing also place in P.A.T. Levene Papers); 210. 3 (17) Levene, P.A.T. Requests for chemicals 210.3 (18).
  Note: At the New York Public Library, Mss and Archive Division (Annex Building, W. 43rd St.) Box 195 Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced Foreign Scholars contains a collection of Levene correspondence with foreign scholars.
  - Administrative correspondence, 3 folders
    Scope and Contents note
    Include a number of handwritten items.
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1905-1920 (Box 1)
      - Exchange with Simon Flexner. Levene writes "... rather miss my comfort and luxury in life than in the laboratory", 1905 August-September
      - With C. Alsbery, U.S. Bureau of Chemistry on certain products in scarce supply because of the war, and handwritten report to H. James in August, 1917 May-August
    - 1921-1929 (Box 1)
      Correspondence on chemotherapy, safety programs and procedures, photographs of Noguchi bust.
      - Letter to Simon Flexner on progress of work on nucleic acids, 1928 December 18
      - Summary of accomplishments of 25 people who had spent time in Levene laboratory, 1929 April 9
      - Reports in letters to Simon Flexner on continuation of vitamin work (May) and in September on the state of nucleic work, 1929
    - 1930-1940 (Box 1)
      - Letter to Simon Flexner on developments in chemistry as a necessary tool in biology, 1930 March 24
      - On the place in bio-chemical developments for Max Bergmann, 1933 November 6
      - Letter to Dr. Dochez in appreciation of Minute adopted by Board of Scientific Directors, 1939 June 14
  - Correspondence with Anne Erickson Levene after P.A.T. Levene's death, 1947 April 2; 1 folder (Box 2)
    Also included is obituary notice and funeral service at her death, 1947 April 2.
  - Medals, 2 items in a package (Box 2)
    - Willard. Gibbs Gold Medal, American Chemical Society Chicago section, 1931
    - W.H. Nichols Gold Medal, American Chemical Society NY section, 1938
  - Citations (2) Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher Mar. 1933 Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften Feb. 1932, 1932-1933; 1 roll (Roll Citations)
  - Collected Works, 13 bound volumes
    Includes one volume of Bibliography.
  - Nucleic Acids by P.A. Levene and Lawrence W. Bass Inscribed to Simon Flexner by P.A. Levene, 1 volume (Box 2)
- American Philosophical Society, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  [Includes Levene/E.G. Conklin, 3 Jun 1940 re Dorothy Wrinch].
- Apparatus (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Includes announcement, instructions, cross-references.
- Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Bertrand Comm, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Besredka, A., 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Best, C.H. - Heparin, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  [Correspondence re Levene purchase of heparin, 1939; also includes 2 letters from Erik Jorpes re heparin, 1935, 1937].
- Bronfenbrenner, Jacques, 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Requests for chemicals and chemical information B-W, 1936-1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Conant, James B., 1928-1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Ethyl Gasoline Corporation, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Fischer, Hermann O.L., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Hopkins, F.G., 1930 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Hudson, Claude S., 1924-1930 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Jorpes, Erik, Rockefeller Fdn. Fellow RIMR 1928-1929. Correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Journal of Biological Chemistry [re publication of papers by Levene, and opinions on papers by others], 1936-1940 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Kuna, Martin [memo re lab accident of, 1930] (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Levene, P.A. [RIMR official, 1935-1939] (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Libby, McNeill and Libby - salmon milts, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Lowry, T.M., 1931 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- [Tables, data, notes, manuscript pages, apparently re paper with R.E. Marker] (Box 3, Folder 14)
- [R.E.] Marker letters, 1934 October 6 1934 October 9 1934 October 13 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Marker correspondence since 1934 [1934-1936], 1932-1936 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Also includes 1932 exchange with Frank Whitemore.
- Marker, R.E., 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Marker, R.E., 1927-1930; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Muskat's Second Paper (Manuscripts], Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Marker discards Feb 1933... (To be separate paper) [Typescript notes], 1933 February; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Liquid Ammonia Method. Methylation Sugars. Muskat. Nov. 16, 1933 [1 page holograph], 1933 November 16; Hollinger 5inch box, 1 page holograph (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Marker discards (are published in other papers), Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Action of Nitrous acids and Nitrosyl chloride on active secondary aliphatic amines (Marker) [Experimental data], Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Experimental notes. Diethyl-n-Amyl Methane, Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Conf. Related Aliphatic Acetates and Ethers, Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Levene-Stevens. Phenylated Carbinols. June 1930. [Holograph and typescript notes and manuscripts], 1930 June; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 6)
- [Experimental data], Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Phenyl acids from Active Secondary Phenyl Chlorides, Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Aliphatic Esters. Marker, Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Marker. Brom Nitrils and Me thoxy Nitrils, Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Monograph. Nuclein (sic) Acids. Chem. Catalog Com. [Royalty statements 1931-40], 1931-1940; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Reviews. Nucleic Acids, Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Oppenheimer, Carl [Editor, Enzymologia 1939-40], 1939-1940; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Pectin [Reprints and correspondence. re material supplied by California Fruit Exchange, 1936-39], 1936-1939; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Senior, James K. [Correspondence 1931-32: discussion of optical acticity and stereochemistry], 1931-1932; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Simms, Henry S., 1931-1932; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Smith, E.B. [Correspondence with RIMR Business Manager 1932-41], 1932-1941; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Spectrograph [re purchase and construction of spectrograph from Physical Lab., Johns Hopkins University, for use by Dr. Alexandre Rothen], 1935; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Steiger, Robert E. [re], 1932; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Stevens, Philip G., 1932; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4)
- Taylor, Fred [re cerebronic acid and lignoceric acid work], 1923-1929; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Van Slyke, Donald D., 1936 1939; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Willard Gibbs Medal [Presented 22 May 1931. Correspondence re meeting, letters and telegrams of congratulation, correspondence. re publication of addresses], 1931 May 22; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Letters from the following Blanksma, J.J., 1913-1914; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Dr. Levene wished to keep this (sic).
- Boutroux, Leon, 1913-1914; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Braun, J.V., 1913; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Abderhalden, Emil, 1929; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Bureau of Standards, 1917-1927; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 2)
  [Includes C.S. Hudson correspondence 1923].
- Benedict and Levene re Klenk and Ditt manuscript, 1935; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Includes Levene comments.
- Cortese, Frank, 1930-1933; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Freudenberg, K., 1932; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Haworth, W.N., 1932-1934; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Hibbert, Harold, 1934; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Hudson, Claude S., 1934; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Irvine, James C., 1932-1933; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 5)
- LaForge, Frederick B. [re; includes statement of LaForge's contributions 1910-34 and bibliography], 1910-1934; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Lowry, T.M., 1933-1934; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 7)
  [Includes correspondence re Levene articles in J. Chem. Phys. and credit to Lowry and others].
- Muskat, Irving E., 1933; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Smith, Theobald, 1929 1933; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Szent-Györgyi, A. [re samples of Vitamin C supplied to Levene], 1933; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Schormüller, Anton, 1931-1934; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 9)
- [Johann Heinrich] Helberger and [Anton] Schormüller [Correspondence re RF fellowships for students of Hans Fischer 1930-31], 1930-1931; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Simms, H.S., 1930-1931; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Simms, H.S., 1928-1930; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Vitamins [Primarily circular letters and memoranda from R. Adams Dutcher, Chairman of Vitamin B. Terminology Comm., 1927-32], 1927-1932; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Bass, L.W. [Includes manuscript of Bass remarks for Nichols Medal meeting, enclosed with Bass/Levene, 27 Feb 1938; also includes correspondence. re Committee on Protein Chemistry of the National Research Council], 1938 February 27; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Bass, L.W., 1928 August-1929 July; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Bass, L.W., 1929 August-1930 June; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Bass, L.W., 1930 August-1932 July; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Christman, Clarence C., 1935-1940; Hollinger 5inch box (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Haller, H.L., 1929-1932 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  [Includes Haller/Levene, 7 Oct 1931, re partial structure of rotenone].
- LaForge, Fred, 1928-1938 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Landsteiner [Karl] (written by Dr. Meyer) [Typescript notes, undated, re preparation of protoalbumose and heteroalbumose] (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Lee, Russell, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Levene, P.A., 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  [Telegrams and correspondence while Levene was away, primarily with Miss Gallagher, PAL secretary].
- Life Extension Institute, 1922-1930 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  [1930 re Mrs. Fejos (Miss Pfaltz), RIMR chemist, 1922-1926].
- Longmans, Green and Co. Ltd., 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Lopez-Susarez, J., 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Lupinek, Bernard, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Northrop, John H., 1929-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  [Primarily re methods and materials, ca 75 pp. Includes Levene/Northrop, 21 Dec 1935, re talk by Dr. Stanley; Nov 1937 correspondence. re work on nucleases and "Dubos enzyme"].
- Stiller, Emil Thomas [Commonwealth Fund Fellow, 1932-34, student of Sir James Irvine], 1932-1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Tipson, Robert Stuart, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  [Includes c.v. and list of publications; correspondence. Sep-Oct 1939 re Tipson and Levene 'Note on "The Structure of Yeast Ribonucleic Acid" in response to paper by Gulland et al in J. Chem. Soc].
- World War I files
  Arrangement
  The correspondence has been rearranged chronologically due to missing folder labels.
  - 1915 April-1917 December (Box 6, Folder 7)
    [Includes circular letter, ca Apr 1917, re Preparedness Census of Chemists by Bureau of Mines and A.C.S.; Dec 1917 ff, re John H. Northrop work on biological production of acetone].
  - 1918 January-August (Box 6, Folder 8)
    [See esp. Levene/Richard M. Pearce, 22 May 1918, re acetone work; correspondence. Jun-Jul re testing of furs; memos ca Jul-Aug re war problems and Levene reply 20 Aug 1918].
  - 1918 September-1919 April 1939 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    [Includes Peyton Rous/Levene exchange Nov 1918 re antiseptic "Vulvine"; Oct 1939 re Nat. Res. Coun. question.].
  - "Sheet 29. Report of processes of Melco Chemical Co. 8/5/18. Aceton production", 1918 May 8 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Monograph; "War Department, Chemical Warfare Service, N.A. Research Division, C.W.S. American University Experiment Station, Washington, D.C. Aug. 18, 1918. Major General W.L. Sibert, Director. G.A. Burrell, Chief of Research Division, Monograph No. 11 Superpalite and Intermediates. Clarence J. West and Herbert S. Harned. Confidential", 1918 August 18 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Monograph; "War Department, Chemical Warfare Service, N.A. Research Division, C.W.S. American University Experiment Station, Washington, D.C. Aug. 18, 1918. Major General W.L. Sibert, Director. G.A. Burrell, Chief of Research Division, Monograph No. 11 Superpalite and Intermediates. Clarence J. West and Herbert S. Harned. Confidential", 1918 August 30 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Monograph No. I Revised. Dichloroethyl sulfide and homologues. Part II. Clarence J. West... ".
- Correspondence
  The following correspondence files were kept in manila envelopes or packages; original labels are included in the new folders wherever possible. The files have been rearranged in alphabetical order.
  - Pectin, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    [Correspondence 1925-26, esp. with California Fruit Growers Exchange. Also includes literature references on pectin].
  - Pincussen article, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    [Correspondence 1926-28 re Levene article for volume edited by Carl Oppenheimer and Ludwig Pincussen, Georg Thieme, publisher].
  - Plimmer re Monograph. Hexosamines and Mucoproteins, 1922-1926 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    [Correspondence with R.H. Plimmer, 1922-26].
  - Pregl apparatus (Box 7, Folder 4)
    [3-page memorandum, undated, "Apparatus purchased from Paul Haack, Wien" and "Apparatus purchased from Eimer and Amend, New York"].
  - Silica Gel Corporation, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    [Correspondence re supply of silica gel to concentrate "growth-promoting principle of yeast". See esp. Levene letter of 14 May 1926, comments on relationship between industrial and scientific labs.].
  - Simms, [Henry S], 1926-1928 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Vitamin Food Corporation, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    [Correspondence with Edward A. Rumely, re supplies of Marmite and Vagex; work on vitamins and nucleic acids. See esp. Rumely/Levene, 20 May 1925 encl. 5-page report on Rumely's visit to Europe, esp. Germany, to study food production. Also includes copies of some published material].
  - Warburg [Otto] Correspondence re glycolysis, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Levene/Warburg, 1924 November 12; 2 pp.
    - Warburg/Levene, 1924 December 1; 1 p.
    - Levene/Warburg, 1924 December 17; 2 pp. and encl. 1 p.
  - Whitmore [Frank C.] Bills, 1925-1927 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    [for chemicals purchased from the Public Health Institute, Chicago].
  - Whitmore. Orders, 1925-1927 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    [Telegrams and correspondence re chemicals].
  - Whitmore, 1925-1927 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    [Gen. correspondence. Jun 1925-Jun 1927 re chemicals, meetings, administration.
    See esp. Levene/Whitmore, 22 Dec 1926, comments on plans for 2nd National Symposium on General Organic Chemistry].
  - Whitmore, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    [Gen. correspondence. Jul 1927-Jul 1928. See esp. Levene/Whitmore, 11 Jan 1928, reply to Whitmore's request for names of foreign chemists for invitation to A.C.S. Institute of Chemistry meeting].
  - Whitmore, 1928-1930 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    [Gen. correspondence. Jul 1928-May 1930].
  - Zunz, Edgard, 1926-1928 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Lecture material
  - Lantern slides for "The relation of chemical structure to optical properties of some simple organic compounds" Meeting, Nat. Acad. Sci. Schnectady, NY, 1928 November 19 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    [holograph and typescript copies].
  - "Chemical structure and optical activity," Lecture at Yale, 1929 March 6 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    [Diagrams and tables].
  - "Chemical structure and optical activity." Address before Organic Symposium, Am. Chem. Soc. at Princeton University Dec 30-Jan 1 [1930-31] [Diagrams], 1930 December 30-1931 January 1 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "Sugars in the service of chemistry." Speech delivered on occasion of award of Hildebrand Medal to Dr. C.S. Hudson in Washington, D.C., 1931 March 26 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    [Holograph and typescripts; galley. Galley and typescript reads "Hillebrand"].
  - "Chemical structure and optical activity." Meeting of Nat. Acad. Sci. April 27, 28, 29 1931. [Diagrams], 1931 April 27-29 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "The revolt of the biochemists." Presentation of the Willard Gibbs Medal, Chicago, May 22, 1931. [Typescripts, galley, holographs], 1931 May 22 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Glucoside formation in the partially substituted sugars". Levene-Raymond Meeting Nat. Acad. Sci., 1931 November 16-18 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    [Tables, graphs; typescript, tables].
  - "On condensation and polymerization in the sugar group." Lecture delivered December 7, 1931 before meeting Am. Chem. Soc. -Rochester Section, 1931 December 7 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    [Diagrams for lantern slides; holograph ms.].
  - "Recent investigations in the field of nucleic acids." Lecture at Columbia Dec. 11, 1931. 12 slides. [Diagrams], 1931 December 11; 12 slides (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Lantern slides for lecture before Organic Symposium of Am. Chem. Soc. at Yale December 28, 1931. "Chemical structure and optical rotation." [Diagrams, tables, memo], 1931 December 28 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Some new contributions to nucleic acid chemistry" Nat. Acad. Sci. Meeting, Washington Read by title only. [Diagrams], 1932 April 25 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Stereochemical tables (Dr. Levene), 1934 January (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Thio Sugars" P.A. Levene and A.L. Raymond. Delivered by Dr. Raymond. Meeting An. Soc. Biol. Chem. Hotel Pennsylvania. [Diagrams], 1934 March 29 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Recent advances in our knowledge of the ribose nucleotides". E.T. Stiller and R.S. Tipson. Staff meeting, 1934 May 11 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    [Holograph and typescript mss.].
  - "[Chemical] structure and optical activity." 24 lantern slides. Johns Hopkins University (Doehme Lecture) [Outline of lecture, diagrams, and tables], 1934 November 16 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Analysis of rotatory dispersion curves of members of homologous series of the type [xx] National Academy of Sciences Meeting by P.A. Leven and A. Rothen, 1935 April 22-24; diagram, Manuscript, Galley (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Lantern slides. Staff lecture. "Chem. structure and optical activity." P.A. Levene and A. Rothen. [Diagrams], 1935 November 25 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - "The absolute conf. of carbinols of the type [xx] by P.A. Levene and A. Rothen. National Academy of Sciences, 1936 April 27 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    [Diagrams, holograph of ms.].
  - "The mechanism of the reaction of substitution and Walden Inversion". P.A. Levene and A. Rothen. Lecture at Nat. Acad. Sci, 1937 April 26 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    [folder empty; envelope re same lecture has manuscript drafts, tables, galley].
  - Lantern slides. "The mechanism of the reaction of substitution." Lecture New York University, 1937 May 7 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    [Diagrams].
  - Staff visit, 1938 January 28 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    [Diagrams, manuscripts of brief talks by various Levene lab. associates.].
  - Charts made in illustration for Staff lecture. Theories of protein structure End of 1700 to 1850, 1938 February 4; 2 sheets (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Lantern slides for Nichols Medal Award Lecture. "Optical rotation as a tool in structural and theoretical chemistry", 1938 March 11 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "Naming the desoxy-sugars, glycals, glycoseens and sugar acids." R. Stuart Tipson. Paper delivered at Milwaukee meeting A.C.S. Sep. 8, 1938. [Typescript], 1938 September 8 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Manuscripts, 1929; Box 9: 5" Hollinger boxes
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Box 9: From P.A. Levene filing cabinet.